Nikolay Karlovich Medtner Papers
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Nikolay Karlovich Medtner Papers 1826-1954 (bulk 1914-1954)
ML31.M43
Medtner, Nikolay Karlovich, 1880-1951
Approximately 2,500 items 11 containers 5.5 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Nikolay Medtner was a Russian-born pianist and composer. The collection documents Medtner's personal life and career and includes correspondence, programs, articles, reviews, clippings, photographs, books with Medtner's annotations, three manuscript scores in Medtner's hand, realia, and other miscellaneous items.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Conus, Leon--Correspondence.; Conus, Olga--Correspondence.; Dhami, Sadhu Singh, 1906-1997--Correspondence.; Dobrowen, Issay, 1893-1953--Correspondence.; Dupré, Marcel, 1886-1971--Correspondence.; Gedike, Aleksandr Fedorovich, 1877-1957--Correspondence.; Godowsky, Leopold, 1870-1938--Correspondence.; Jaya Chamaraja Wadiyar, 1919- --Correspondence.; Medtner, Anna Mikhaĭlovna, 1877-1965--Correspondence.; Medtner, Nikolay Karlovich, 1880-1951--Archives.; Medtner, Nikolay Karlovich, 1880-1951--Correspondence.; Medtner, Nikolay Karlovich, 1880-1951--Manuscripts.; Medtner, Nikolay Karlovich, 1880-1951--Photographs.; Medtner, Nikolay Karlovich, 1880-1951.; Medtner, Nikolay Karlovich, 1880-1951.; Medtner, Nikolay Karlovich, 1880-1951. Muza i moda.; Metner, Ėmiliĭ Karlovich, 1872-1936--Correspondence.; Moiseiwitsch, Benno, 1890-1963--Correspondence.; Rachmaninoff, Natalie--Correspondence.; Rachmaninoff, Sergei, 1873-1943--Correspondence.; Rachmaninoff, Sergei, 1873-1943--Photographs.; Satina, Sophia, 1879-1975--Correspondence.; Sorabji, Kaikhosru Shapurji, 1892-1988--Correspondence.; Turcotte, J. G., abbé--Correspondence.
Subjects
Composers--Russia.; Music--Manuscripts.; Pianists--Russia.
Form/Genre
Artifacts (Object genre); Clippings (Information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographic prints.; Programs (Documents)
Administrative Information
Provenance
Acquired in 1953 as a gift from Anna Mikhaĭlovna Bratenskaya Medtner (widow of Nikolay Medtner), with additional gifts by Sofiia Aleksandrovna Satina, Olga Conus (Konius), and Dr. Alfred J. Swan.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Other Repositories
Institutions with significant Medtner holdings include: the Glinka Museum in Moscow (a large source of Medtner materials, especially pre-1921); British Library in London (six boxes of materials collected by Medtner pupil Edna Iles which includes manuscripts, correspondence, notes, and scores annotated in Medtner's hand); University of Leeds Special Collections Library in England (an unknown quantity of private papers, diaries, letters, photographs, ephemera and audio cassettes presumably related to Medtner's acquaintance with Richard Holt); University of Virginia Special Collections Library in Charlottesville, Va. (the Alfred Swan Papers includes correspondence, diaries, and other source materials for Swan's writings on Medtner); Library and Archives of Canada in Ottawa (the Alfred Laliberté fonds Collection contains significant correspondence, a few manuscripts, and other materials); and a privately owned archive recently acquired by Yevgeny Sudbin.
Related Material
The Library of Congress Music Division holds numerous special collections that contain correspondence, music, or publications related to Nikolay Medtner. These include: the Rachmaninoff Archives (documents); the
Jascha Heifetz Collection
(including holograph scores and printed scores of Heifetz's arrangement of Medtner's Skazka, op. 20/1); the
Nicolas Slonimsky Collection
(printed scores that include Medtner's music; pamphlet on Medtner by Richard Holt); the
Serge Koussevitzky Archive
(two letters by Medtner to Koussevitzky); the
Moldenhauer Archive
(a holograph manuscript, including corrections/annotations of Medtner's Elegie, op. 52/3); and the
Boris Koutzen Collection
(printed scores of Medtner's Violin Sonata, op. 21 and Nocturne, op. 16/1, including performance annotations presumably by Koutzen).
Access and Restrictions
The Nikolay Karlovich Medtner Papers are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1872 Ėmiliĭ Karlovich Metner (Nikolay Medtner's brother) born
1877 Anna Mikhaĭlovna Bratenskaya Medtner (Nikolay Medtner's wife) born
1880, Jan. 5 Nikolay Karlovich Medtner born, Moscow, Russia
1890 Entered Moscow Conservatory
1897 Completed Acht Stimmungsbilder, op. 1 (published 1903)
1900 Graduated from Moscow Conservatory with small gold medal
1902 Ėmiliĭ and Anna married
1903 Composed Piano Sonata no. 1, F minor, op. 5 (published 1904)
1909 Appointed Professor at Moscow Conservatory
1911 Composed Piano Sonata in E minor, op. 25, no. 2: Night wind (published 1912)
1918 Composed Piano Concerto no. 1, C minor, op. 33 (published 1921)
1919, June 21 Nikolay married Anna Medtner (formerly wife of Ėmiliĭ Karlovich Metner)
1921 Moved to Berlin
1922 Composed Sonata in A minor, op. 38, no. 1: Reminiscenza
1924 Moved to Paris
1927 Composed Piano Concerto no. 2, C minor, op. 50 (published 1928)
1935 Publication of Nikolay Medtner's treatise Muza i Moda, in Russian (English translation, 1951) Moved to London
1936 Ėmiliĭ Karlovich Metner died
1943 Composed Piano Concerto no. 3, E major, op. 60: Ballade (published 1951)
1946 Met Jayachamaraja Wodeyar Bahadur (the last Maharaja of the princely state of Mysore); the Maharaja financed the recording of a large number of Medtner's works
1948 Composed Piano Quintet in C major, op. posth. (published 1955)
1949 Medtner Society founded by Jayachamaraja Wodeyar Bahadur
1951, Nov. 13 Died at Golders Green, London
1965 Anna Medtner died
Scope and Content Note
The Nikolay Karlovich Medtner Papers contain letters, programs, clippings, photographs, scores, books, realia, and other items related to Medtner's family life and career as a concert pianist. These materials date from 1826-1954, with the majority dating from 1914-1954. The Correspondence series takes up nearly half the collection and consists of family and general correspondence written between 1914 and 1954, containing over 1,900 letters in Russian, German, English, and French. Family correspondence (1914-1936) consists of approximately 500 letters by Nikolay and/or wife Anna to Ėmiliĭ Karlovich Metner with over 400 letters in reply. The general correspondence (1921-1954) contains significant letters and transcripts to and from Sergei and Nataliia Rachmaninoff, Leon and Olga Conus, Sofiia Aleksandrovna Satina, Konstantin Klimov, Madeleine Laliberté (Mrs. Albert Laliberté), Bernard and Cecile Pinsonneault, Abbé J.G. Turcotte, and smaller holdings of letters by other musicians and admirers. This series also contains condolence letters sent to Anna upon Nikolay’s death and a large quantity of unidentified letters.
The Programs series largely documents concerts given by Medtner in the U.S., Canada, Europe, and Russia between 1907 and 1946. There are also programs featuring Medtner’s works, presumably collected by the family. The Articles series (1910-1952) consists chiefly of newspaper clippings (often collected in scrapbooks, transcribed, and occasionally translated) and several longer articles written about Medtner. In addition, there is a brief article written by Medtner on the topic of musical inspiration. Aside from one photograph of Medtner himself, the Photography series is confined mostly to inscribed photographs of various musicians presented to Medtner, including two by Rachmaninoff.
The Miscellany series includes analytical notes, advertisements, and reviews pertaining to the Medtner Society's recordings; catalogues from Ėmiliĭ's publishing house Musaget' dating from 1912-1913; a 1927 address (with English translation) signed by 111 Moscow musicians and given to Medtner upon his visit to Russia; a diploma (1928) from the Royal Academy of Music; and a humorous scroll dated 1936. A bronze bust of Medtner executed by Karen Vogel and a posthumous plaster cast of Medtner's hands are included in this collection. Among the books are poetic works by Pushkin and Tiutchev, with Medtner's annotations, Medtner's personal copy of Muza i moda, and a copy of Ėmiliĭ's Modernizm’ i Muzika.
The Music series consists of printed scores and three manuscripts in Medtner's hand: Russian Round Dance, op. 58, no. 1; a 1896 work entitled Prelude, piano, E♭ minor, dedicated to Anna (possibly reworked as Op. 14/1); and an early vocal piece entitled Romance, also dedicated to Anna (possibly reworked as Op. 3/1). Among the printed music holdings is a bound volume containing musical settings to Pushkin's texts by various composers compiled by V.A. Kiselev as well as a printed score to Arthur Lourié’s Formes en l’air, with a written dedication to Medtner initialed by Rachmaninoff.
A few explanatory words regarding transliteration of the composer's surname: although the correct transliteration of the Russian-born composer's surname would be more precisely rendered according to the Library of Congress's transliteration system as "Metner," the composer himself favored the Germanic spelling of his name, "Medtner," in Roman script; the latter form, through which the composer gained renown in the West, has therefore been retained within this document. Conversely, the Library of Congress transliteration system has been adhered to in transliterating the name of the composer's brother, Ėmiliĭ Metner (who neither cultivated a career in the West, nor adopted the Germanic spelling of his surname). Alternate spellings for Russian names and titles that appear in this finding aid--including those defined by convention as well as standardized transliteration--have been included in an appendix to facilitate searching. A modified Library of Congress transliteration system, excluding ligatures and accent marks, has been adopted in this finding aid.
Organization of the Nikolay Karlovich Medtner Papers
The Nikolay Karlovich Medtner Papers are organized in seven series:
Correspondence, 1914-1954
Programs, 1907-1953
Articles, 1910-1952
Photographs, 1922-1951
Miscellany, 1912-1951
Books, 1826-1948
Music, 1896-circa 1940
http://lccn.loc.gov/2011570510
Container List
- Correspondence, 1914-1954 (Box 1-5)
  Letters by Nikolay and/or Anna Medtner and Ėmiliĭ Karlovich Metner (Nikolay's brother) to one another, condolence notes/letters written by others to Anna Medtner at the time of Nikolay's death in 1951, and correspondence by friends and colleagues of Nikolay Medtner.
  The series is arranged into two subseries: the first contains correspondence between Medtner family members; the second contains correspondence by non-family members to Nikolay Medtner. Arranged alphabetically by correspondent's last name, and chronologically therein.
  - Medtner Family, 1914-1951
    - Ėmiliĭ to Nikolay and Anna, 1917-1936 (Box-folder 1/1-17)
    - Anna to Ėmiliĭ, 1914 (Box-folder 2/1)
    - Anna and Nikolay to Ėmiliĭ, 1914-1936, undated (Box-folder 2/2-15; 3/1-4)
    - Condolence letters/notes to Anna Medtner, 1951, undated (Box-folder 3/5-7)
  - General, 1921-1954
    - Alexander, Arthur, 1928-1951, undated (Box-folder 3/8)
    - Armin, George, 1926-1938, undated (Box-folder 3/9)
    - Arnson, Lyuta, 1928-1930 (Box-folder 3/10)
    - "A" miscellaneous, 1926-1949 (Box-folder 3/11)
    - Bax, Arnold, undated (Box-folder 3/12)
    - Bentner, Marie Auguste, 1932-1945 (Box-folder 3/13)
    - Bernhard, Isolda, 1928 (Box-folder 3/14)
    - Binstead, S.T. and Ann, 1947-1951 (Box-folder 3/15)
    - Bloch, J. H., 1928-1933 (Box-folder 3/16)
    - Blom, Eric, 1948-1952 (Box-folder 3/17)
    - Braithware, Sam Hartley, 1930-1944 (Box-folder 3/18)
    - Braunstein, Albert, 1951 (Box-folder 3/19)
    - Bühler, Lenox, 1945-1951 (Box-folder 3/20)
    - "B" miscellaneous, 1928-1952 (Box-folder 3/21)
    - Catterall, Yvonne and Hugh, 1950-1951 and undated (Box-folder 3/22)
    - Chamberland, Albert, 1927-1951 (Box-folder 3/23)
    - Chekhova, Vseniya, 1931-1934 (Box-folder 3/24)
    - Cloutier, Leo, 1947-1952 (Box-folder 3/25)
    - Conus, Leon and Olga, 1936-1945 (Box-folder 3/26-30)
    - Conus, Olga, 1946-1952 and undated (Box-folder 4/1-3)
    - Conus, Sergei, 1947-1951 (Box-folder 4/4)
    - Conus, Tatiana, 1931-1951 (Box-folder 4/5)
    - "C" miscellaneous, 1921-1943 (Box-folder 4/6)
    - Décarie, Annette, 1927-1934 (Box-folder 4/7)
    - Decaux, Abel, 1927-1928 (Box-folder 4/8)
    - De Jersey, Everal, 1928 (Box-folder 4/9)
    - Denissoff, J., dobrowen 1933 (Box-folder 4/10)
    - Dhami, Sadhu Singh, 1944-1948 (Box-folder 4/11)
    - Dobrowen, Issay, 1948-1951 and undated (Box-folder 4/12)
    - Dobuzhinsky, Mstislav, 1948-1951 and undated (Box-folder 4/13)
    - Dupré, Marcel, 1926-1951 (Box-folder 4/14)
    - "D" miscellaneous, 1928-1950 (Box-folder 4/15)
    - "E" miscellaneous, 1939 (Box-folder 4/16)
    - Fortier, Florestine, 1930-1932 (Box-folder 4/17)
    - "F" miscellaneous, 1928-1953 and undated (Box-folder 4/18)
    - Gedike, Aleksandr Fedorovich, 1926 (Box-folder 4/19)
    - Gélinas, Rosaire, 1936 (Box-folder 4/20)
    - Godowsky, Leopold, 1926 (Box-folder 4/21)
    - "G" miscellaneous, 1928-1934 (Box-folder 4/22)
    - Harrison, Eric, 1944 (Box-folder 4/23)
    - Hervé, Henriette, 1922 (Box-folder 4/24)
    - Hill, Valentina, 1951 (Box-folder 4/25)
    - Holt, Richard, 1948-1951 (Box-folder 4/26)
    - "H" miscellaneous, 1927-1949 (Box-folder 4/27)
    - Iles, Edna, 1954, Also includes: handwritten eight page narrative by Iles; 1946 and 1948 concert programs. (Box-folder 4/28)
    - Jacobson, Myron, 1931 and undated (Box-folder 4/29)
    - Jaya Chamaraja Wadiyar (Maharaja of Mysore), 1946-1951 (Box-folder 4/30)
    - "J" miscellaneous, 1937 (Box-folder 4/31)
    - Kedroff, Nikolai, 1938-1952 and undated (Box-folder 4/32)
    - Klimov, Konstantin, 1932-1939 and undated (Box-folder 4/33)
    - Klimov, Konstantin, 1940-1953 (Box-folder 4/34)
    - Knatchbule, Dora, 1942-1944 and undated (Box-folder 4/35)
    - "K" miscellaneous, 1923-1948 and undated (Box-folder 4/36)
    - Laliberté, Madeleine, 1950-1951 (Box-folder 4/37)
    - Langlet, Nina Nikolaevna, 1948-1950 (Box-folder 4/38)
    - Legge, Walter see Box 5, Schwarzkopf, Elizabeth
    - "L" miscellaneous, 1928-1952 (Box-folder 4/39)
    - Marie-Stéphanie, Sœur, 1928-1951 (Box-folder 4/40)
    - Marx, Joseph, 1949-1951 (Box-folder 4/41)
    - Menzel, Richard, 1948 (Box-folder 4/42)
    - Mettsel, Vladimir, 1943-1947 (Box-folder 4/43)
    - Moiseiwitsch, Benno, 1943-1951 (Box-folder 4/44)
    - Mutch, Isabel, 1934-1936 and undated (Box-folder 4/45)
    - "M" miscellaneous, 1927-1948 and undated (Box-folder 4/46)
    - Newman, Ernest, 1932 (Box-folder 4/47)
    - "N" miscellaneous, 1932 and undated (Box-folder 4/48)
    - Olenina-d'Alʹgeĭm, M. A. (Mariia Alekseevna), undated (Box-folder 4/49)
    - Orlov, G., 1929-1951 (Box-folder 4/50)
    - Paĭchadze, Gavril Gregorevich, 1951 (Box-folder 5/1)
    - Patience, Ernest, 1923 and undated (Box-folder 5/2)
    - Pinsonneault, Bernard, 1949-1952 (Box-folder 5/3)
    - Pinsonneault, Cécile, 1950-1951 (Box-folder 5/4)
    - "P" miscellaneous, 1928-1950 (Box-folder 5/5)
    - Rachmaninoff, Natalie, 1922-1949 and undated (Box-folder 5/6)
    - Rachmaninoff, Sergei, 1912, 1921-1939 and undated (Box-folder 5/7-9)
      Includes transcriptions of letters, undated letters, notes.
    - Randle, Maud, undated (Box-folder 5/10)
    - Ritchie, Margaret, 1948-1952 (Box-folder 5/11)
    - "R" miscellaneous, 1944-1951 (Box-folder 5/12)
    - Sabaniev, Alyota, 1937-1950 and undated (Box-folder 5/13)
    - Sabline, E., 1942-1944 (Box-folder 5/14)
    - Samofnikova, Natasha, 1924-1928 (Box-folder 5/15)
    - Satin, Vladimir Alexandrovich, 1921 and undated (Box-folder 5/16)
    - Satina, Sofiia Aleksandrovna, 1945-1953 and undated (Box-folder 5/17-18)
    - Schwarzkopf, Elizabeth, 1951, Additional writing added by Walter Legge. (Box-folder 5/19)
    - Segovia, Andrés, 1923 and undated (Box-folder 5/20)
    - Smith, Cyril, 1945-1948 (Box-folder 5/21)
    - Sorabji, Kaikhosru Shapurji, 1946-1952 (Box-folder 5/22)
    - Stegmann, G. F., 1949 (Box-folder 5/23)
    - Stone, Christopher, 1948-1951 and undated (Box-folder 5/24)
    - Swan, Alfred J., 1948 (Box-folder 5/25)
    - "S" miscellaneous, 1928-1952 (Box-folder 5/26)
    - Thompson, J. Antonio, 1933-1934 (Box-folder 5/27)
    - Turcotte, J. G., abbé, 1929-1951 (Box-folder 5/28)
    - "T" miscellaneous, 1927-1952 (Box-folder 5/29)
    - "V" miscellaneous, 1928-1934 (Box-folder 5/30)
    - Wolfman, J., 1931-1934 (Box-folder 5/31)
    - Wolkonsky, Irina Rachmaninoff, 1930-1952 (Box-folder 5/32)
    - Wood, Henry J., 1944 (Box-folder 5/33)
    - Wüllner, Ludwig, 1927-1928 (Box-folder 5/34)
    - "W" miscellaneous, 1928-1950 and undated (Box-folder 5/35)
    - Yasser, Joseph, 1927-1952 (Box-folder 5/36)
    - Zernova, Militsa, 1944-1948 (Box-folder 5/37)
    - Zhorzh, Sasha (?), 1927-1937 and undated (Box-folder 5/38)
    - "X - Z" miscellaneous, 1952 and undated (Box-folder 5/39)
    - "Constance" (unidentified surname), 1952 (Box-folder 5/40)
    - "Lelya (Lelia)" (unidentified surname), undated (Box-folder 5/41)
    - Unidentifed (miscellaneous correspondence), 1912-1952 and undated (Box-folder 5/42)
    - Unidentified (multiple signatures), 1946 and undated (Box-folder 5/43)
    - Unidentified (miscellaneous - various addresses), 1921 and undated (Box-folder 5/44)
    - Unidentified (notes by Nikolai or Anna Medtner) 1954 and undated (Box-folder 5/45)
    - Unidentified (letters written in a similar hand), 1923 and undated (Box-folder 5/46)
    - Unidentified (with attributive annotations by Anna Medtner?), 1924-1951 and undated (Box-folder 5/47)
- Programs, 1907-1953 (Box 6)
  Programs for concerts given by Medtner in the U.S., Canada, Europe, and Russia, as well as programs featuring performances of Medtner's works by others.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Concerts given by Medtner, 1907-1946 and undated
    - 1907-1946 and undated (Box-folder 6/1-4)
      March 13, 1930 program autographed by Sir Dan Godfrey, conductor.
  - Concerts of Medtner's works given by other musicians, 1920-1953 and undated
    - 1920-1953 and undated (Box-folder 6/5-8)
- Articles, 1910-1952 (Box 7)
  Newspaper clippings (often collected in scrapbooks, transcribed, and occasionally translated) and several longer articles written about Medtner. Includes a brief article written by Medtner on musical inspiration.
  Arranged alphabetically by author's last name, and chronologically therein.
  - Alexander, Arthur. "Nicolas Medtner: an appreciation," Tempo, no. 22 (Winter 1951-1952) (Box-folder 7/1)
  - Armin, George, editor. [Several articles featuring Medtner] Der Stimmwart, 2-4, 6. Jahrgang, (1926-1930), Collection of individual issues of Der Stimmwart, featuring articles on Medtner. Several typed transcripts of articles from this serial are also included. (Box-folder 7/2)
  - Clippings, 1910-1950 and undated (Box-folder 7/3-12)
  - Clippings. Unbound book of transcripts, 1924-1940 and undated, Includes an unbound book (109 pages) containing typed transcripts taken from newspapers and articles. (Box-folder 7/13)
  - Clippings album, 1932 (Box-folder 7/14)
  - Clippings. Preservation photocopies, 1929-1946 (Box-folder 7/15)
  - Gestlé, Henry S. "The Piano music of Nicolai Medtner," Musical Quarterly, 10, no. 4 (October 1924) (Box-folder 7/16)
  - Il'in, Ivan. [Unidentified article], [Unidentified journal], no. 7 (1929), Includes a letter (dated 1952) to Anna Medtner, presumably from Il'in. (Box-folder 7/17)
  - Medtner, Nikolai. "Opinions: On Inspiration," The Chesterian, 10, no. 73 (September-October 1928) (Box-folder 7/18)
  - Miller, Sidney. "Medtner's Piano Music," The Musical Times, 82, nos. 1184-1185 (October-November 1941), Two copies. (Box-folder 7/19)
  - Riesemann, Oskar von. "Nikolai Medtner," The Sackbut, (May 1925) (Box-folder 7/20)
  - Riesemann, Oskar von. "Nikolai Medtner," Rheinische Musik- und Theater Zeitung, XXV. Jahrgang, nr. 41-42, November 22, 1924 (Box-folder 7/20)
  - Swan, Alfred J. "Medtner," The Musical Times, 955, no. 63 (September 1, 1922) (Box-folder 7/21)
  - Swan, Alfred J. "Medtner and the Music of our Time," Music and Letters, January 1927 (Box-folder 7/21)
  - Swan, Alfred J. "Nicholas Medtner," The Chesterian, 10, no. 75 (December 1928) (Box-folder 7/21)
  - Swan, Alfred J. [Unidentified article] [Unidentified journal], (1945), Russian language publication containing article featuring Rachmaninoff. (Box-folder 7/21)
  - Swan, Alfred J. and Katherine. "Rachmaninoff: Personal Reminiscences - Part I," Musical Quarterly, 30, no. 1 (January 1944) (Box-folder 7/22)
  - [Unidentified]. [Unidentified article], Cahiers Periodiques, (1949) (Box-folder 7/23)
- Photographs, 1922-1951, undated (Box 8)
  Chiefly photographs of various musicians inscribed to Nikolay Medtner. Included are two inscribed photographs of Rachmaninoff and a photograph of Medtner.
  Arranged alphabetically by last name of individual, and chronologically therein.
  - Armin, George, undated, Inscribed to Medtner. (Box-folder 8/1)
  - Armin, George and Ludwig Wüllner, July 26, 1934, Note written to Medtner from Armin on verso. (Box-folder 8/1)
  - Decaux, Abel, undated, Inscribed. (Box-folder 8/1)
  - Dobrowen, Issay, June 8, 1947, Inscribed. (Box-folder 8/1)
  - Dupré, Marcel, October 7, 1935, Inscribed. (Box-folder 8/1)
  - Dusseau, Jeanne, undated, Inscribed to Medtner. (Box-folder 8/1)
  - Fortier, Florestine, December 1929, Inscribed to Anna and "Nicola." (Box-folder 8/2)
  - Fortier, Florestine and Leopold, December 1929, Inscribed to Medtner. (Box-folder 8/2)
  - Katuar, G. (Georgiĭ), undated, Not signed. Photograph has been identified as: "The composer, Georg Catoire." (Box-folder 8/2)
  - Laliberté, Alfred, 1927, 1931 and undated, Four inscribed photographs, one being an image of Laliberté's music room. (Box-folder 8/2)
  - Makushina, Tatiana, 1929, Inscribed. (Box-folder 8/2)
  - Marx, Joseph, 1951, Inscribed on verso. (Box-folder 8/2)
  - Medtner, Nikolay, 1922, Inscribed with musical quotation. (Box-folder 8/2)
  - Rachmaninoff, Sergei, 1925, Inscribed. (Box-folder 8/3)
  - Rachmaninoff, Sergei, 1930, Inscribed. (Box-folder 8/3)
  - Santagano, Elisabeth, 1926, Inscribed. (Box-folder 8/3)
  - Turcotte, J. G., abbé, undated, Inscribed. (Box-folder 8/3)
  - Wüllner, Ludwig, July 1934, Inscribed.; Two photographs. (Box-folder 8/3)
  - Zimmermann, Wilhelm, undated, Inscribed. (Box-folder 8/3)
- Miscellany, 1912-1951, undated (Box 8-9)
  Analytical notes, advertisements, and reviews pertaining to the Medtner Society's issued recordings; catalogues of 1912-1913 of Ėmiliĭ Metner's publishing house Musaget'; a 1927 address (with English translation) signed by 111 Moscow musicians given to Medtner upon his visit to Russia; a diploma (dated 1928) from the Royal Academy of Music on the occasion of Medtner's election as an honorary member; and a humorous banner given to Medtner from Russian friends soon after his arrival in London in 1936. A bronze bust of Medtner executed by Czech sculptor Karen Vogel and a posthumous plaster cast of Medtner's hands are also included in this collection.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject, and chronologically therein.
  - Address presented to Nikolay Medtner upon his return to Russia, 1927 (Box-folder 8/4)
    The original address was signed by 111 musicians.